כתיב, Katoov, good תענית אסתר נדחה. Ta'anis Esther Nidcheh. We pick up
today's דף, Daf, דף מ"ו. Daf Mem Vav. We pick up at
the middle of מ"ה עמוד ב'. Mem Hey Amud Bais. And we
are in the debate between רבא Rava and אביי. Abaye. Oh, we
have this lovely drawing on the board, but it's not relevant for
us, unfortunately. We have the debate between רבא Rava and אביי Abaye
in terms of when an אומן Uman does not have a חזקה,
Chazakah, which is what the משנה Mishnah says. And there's basically two
axes to look at this on, okay? So again, one axis is
the axis of עדים, Eidim, right there עדים Eidim that the person
gave it to the אומן Uman like to fix, you know, to
let's say to dry clean his clothes or not. So on that
there's with עדים Eidim
and no עדים, Eidim, okay? And then there's the axis of whether
it was ראה? Rao? Want to come through here, Joe? Okay.
And then there's the axis of whether it was ראה, Rao, right,
did you see him in possession of it? So here's ראה Rao
and לא ראה, Lo Rao, you did not see him. Okay, see
in possession.
So those are the two relevant factors. All right, let's sort of
I'm not sure if this is helpful or not. Okay. So those
are the two relevant factors. All right, so what's the story? So
the case that obviously it's no חזקה Chazakah is you saw you
give it to the dry cleaner, witnesses saw you give it to
the dry cleaner to clean, and you currently see it in his
hand. That's no חזקה, Chazakah, we can all agree on that. The
obvious case that there would be a חזקה Chazakah is nobody saw
you give it to the dry cleaner, and nobody saw him right
now in possession of it, so he could claim he never got
it, he could claim he got it, he gave it back, so
of course in this case there would be a חזקה. Chazakah. And
the question is what about these two
axes, which is sort of the dominant of these criteria? So רבא
Rava says the dominant criteria is the issue of עדים. Eidim. When
there are עדים, Eidim, this is what רבא Rava says, there's always
there's never going to be a חזקה. Chazakah. Once you know that
the person got it for the purpose of dry cleaning, then he
is not even if you're not seeing him in possession of it,
he's not believed to say that he, you know, that he gave
you back his טלית, tallis, he's not believed to say that he
bought the טלית tallis from you.
And that's based on the principle that המפקיד אצל חברו בעדים צריך
להחזירו בעדים. Hamapkid Etzel Chaveiro Be'Eidim Tzarich Lehachaziro Be'Eidim. If you gave
it to him with witnesses that not as a gift, you know,
to dry clean as a פיקדון, pikadon, he has to give it
back to you with witnesses and if he hasn't given back, right,
I understand, if he isn't giving back with witnesses, then he's not
believed to say that he gave it back to you, so similarly
he's not believed to say he bought it. So if you stop
for a moment and think about this and this is the point
the גמרא Gemara is going to make at the end, then this
really has nothing to do with him being an אומן. Uman. This
really has to do with anybody who receives something with witnesses, right,
is not believed to say that he gave it back. So if
I gave something to my friend Eli there to watch for me,
and he said he gave it back, he said he bought it
from me, he also doesn't have a חזקה, Chazakah, right, because he's
not believed to say he gave it back unless there are witnesses.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to challenge at the
end according to רבא. Rava. That what רבא Rava is saying has
really nothing to do with the fact that he's an אומן. Uman.
Okay, תוספות Tosafot explains how it still could be connected, but that's
the basic point. אביי Abaye makes a much more reasonable assertion. אביי
Abaye says no no no, it's not about whether there are עדים,
Eidim, it's about whether you see it in his hand. And this
works much more with the idea of an אומן. Uman. Okay, if
you see an אומן Uman going around with something that we knew
was somebody else's clothes, and it's the type of clothes you give
to this person,
meaning if you see a dry cleaner wearing my socks, okay, that
wouldn't be a problem because you don't dry clean socks. If you
see a leather worker wearing my nice cloth suit, that wouldn't be
a problem, but if you see the dry cleaner wearing my suit,
okay, even if we don't know that I gave it to him
for dry cleaning, that's the point that אומן אין לו חזקה. Uman
Ein Lo Chazakah. Because he is the type of a person whom
you give your suit to clean and he's wearing a suit that
you knew was yours, there is no חזקה. Chazakah. And that's what
אביי Abaye says. אביי Abaye says if you didn't see it in
his hand, right, then אביי Abaye says then okay, he could claim
he doesn't have it at all, so he's believed to say he
owns it. But if you see him with it, he's not believed
to say that he owns it. A normal person if I'm holding
something we knew is yours, I'm believed to say it's mine. But
if I'm a dry cleaner holding onto your suit, even if we
have no witnesses that you gave it to me, but by virtue
of the fact that I'm the type of person you give suits
to clean, okay, my holding onto your suit is אין לו חזקה
Ein Lo Chazakah and that's what אביי Abaye says. Okay, so אביי
Abaye focuses on the ראה Rao
and רבא Rava focuses on the עדים Eidim which is not really
unique to the idea of an אומן. Uman. Yes, David.
So two questions. That is one is, we have not seen אביי
Abaye. *Abaye* say this position yet in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Did we not? Correct.
We’ve only gotten a question from אביי Abaye. *Abaye*.
מיתיבי *Meisive* אביי Abaye *Abaye* עבד *eved*...
where is that, where are we?
Maybe you're right, maybe it was just implicit in אביי'ס *Abaye's* challenges.
That's right. Okay. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* then goes on to
try to prove that it's all about רבא Rava *Rava*. Right, but
it's not, he never stated it, as right, so great.
Okay, the second thing is is that, at least at the moment,
where we are in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, is רבא Rava *Rava*
just...
I know, I was about to get to that. Okay, fine. That's
okay. So then anyway we brought evidence that showed that you actually
it was only a problem when it was רבא Rava *Rava*. There
was a ברייתא braita, *brayta* that made it clear it was only
a problem when it was רבא Rava *Rava*. So then רבא Rava.
*Rava* wound up saying fine fine, so it's not a חזקה chazaka
*chazakah* only when you have both. Only when it's רבא Rava. *Rava*
and there are עדים edim *eidim*, only in the box that we
can all agree on. Right? Which is a very narrow case of
אין לו חזקה ein lo chazaka. *ein lo chazakah*. But that is
because there was a ברייתא braita *brayta* that was brought that seemed
to be pretty good evidence that the issue was רבא Rava *Rava*.
So רבא Rava *Rava* was a relevant criteria. So that led רבא
Rava, *Rava* to limit himself just to this box. Okay, so and
that’s where we left off yesterday. So let’s continue. Yes.
You see me walking down the street with your suit. Yes. And
you say what are you doing with my suit? It's mine.
Right, and you
and I say to you
I bought it from you.
No, I say to you of course it's your suit, but you
lent it to me. Don't you remember? I can wear it for
the next month and a half. So I’m believed.
Yes, because you could say you own it, sure. Okay, so alright,
as- what you see, you see.
You see it in possession.
We see my suit in possession of the dry cleaner. You see
you know that he's holding on right now to my suit. If
you don't know he could say what the heck can you talking
about, I never got your you know, I don't have your suit
you're just making this all up. But no, we know that that's
my suit in your hand. You're claiming it’s purchased. There's no believability,
your dry cleaner with my suit you're not believed to say it's
purchased. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Let's go. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay, מיתיבי *mative* רבא
Rava. *Rava* now six lines from the bottom, one two three, seven
lines from the bottom, מיתיבי *mative* רבא Rava *Rava* end of the
line, לסיועי *lisei’ei* לרבה *l’Rabba*. So רבא Rava *Rava* now raised her
challenge to support רבה *Rabba*. So David you make a good point,
like he didn't say he's he challenged אביי Abaye *Abaye* because אביי
*Abaye* didn't really assert a position, he was just trying to challenge
רבא Rava *Rava*. So now רבא Rava *Rava* challenges the opposing position.
רבא'ס *Rava's* going to try to support רבה *Rabba*. Let's take a
look. נותן טליתו לאומן *Noten taliso l’uman*. אומן uman *Uman* אומר *omer*
שתים קצצת לי *shtayim katzatzta li*, והוא אומר *vehahhu omer* לא קצצתי
לך אלא אחת *lo katzatzti lecha ela achas*. Okay, so I gave
my טלית tallit *tallis* to Mike over there, because you're here you're
always sitting right here, to Mike to do it for dry cleaning,
then I come to pick it up, I'm telling you this is
really why you need a whole system of like receipts and whatever.
I come to Mike to pick it up and I say let
me have my suit, Mike says sure twenty dollars and I say
we don't we said ten dollars. Okay, so who's believed? Okay,
so here two and one. Okay, so לא קצצתי לך אלא אחת
*lo katzatzti lecha ela achas*. כל זמן שהטלית ביד אומן uman *Kol
zeman she-tallis beyad uman*, על הבעל הבית להביא ראיה re'iyah *al habaal
habayis l’havi re'iyah*. Okay, as long as Mike's holding on to my
suit, I have to prove that we said ten dollars if I
can't he's believed to say twenty. Why? מיגו migo *migo* because he
could have well, מיגו migo *migo* because he could have said that
he that I gave it to him.
Okay, and give me fifty.
What? Okay, אין הכי נמי *ein hachi nami*, there'd be a point
where we might say that a מיגו *migo* wouldn't work if it's
blatantly false. But anyway. Okay, now the point so relevant point for
us being the reason Mike's believed just because of how much we
agreed upon is because he's believed to say that he owns it.
Okay, so let's keep on going. Now, נתנה לו *nasnah lo* נתנה
לו *nasnah lo*, now if let's say Mike already gave me the
suit and we're debating how much I owe him, so בזמנו נשבע
ונוטל nishba venotel. *bizmano nishba venotel*. Once it's in the normal time
period right before the sunset etc., when I'm supposed to pay Mike
up, there's a תקנת חכמים *takanas chachamim* that because I'm too distracted
with having to pay all my various workers, we actually trust Mike
in that situation while it's still בזמנו *bizmano* and he can take
a שבועה *shvua* and get what he says we agreed upon. עבר
זמנו aver zmano *Avar zemano* once the time is passed since Mike
is being so like you know not careful, negligent, to let the
to let it go beyond the normal time, we
we're concerned maybe I already paid him or we don't believe him
as much, and in that case and in that case you gave
it back to me, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah,
*hamotzi mechavero alav hare'iyah*. He has to bring a proof. Now by
the way, how עבר זמנו zmano *avar zemano* is relevant תוספות Tosefot
*Tosfos* raises the question the issue, it doesn't make work so well
here because the normal case that a אומן uman. *uman* or whatever
a שכיר *sachir* a hired hand is נשבע ונוטל *nishba venotel*, that's
when we're debating whether I paid him at all or not. Okay,
and there it makes sense, like here it is it's the end
of the day, I'm distracted I have to pay all my workers,
and I don't remember if I paid this guy or not, so
a the בעל הבית ba'al habayis. *baal habayis* is distracted, okay, and
therefore we can say that as long as the guy makes a
שבועה *shvua* he'll be believed, but that's why we also say that
if it's now after the time of paying, if I really hadn't
paid Mike, why did he wait two days to until ask me
for it, right? If he really hadn't paid him he would have
demanded earlier. So that idea that it matters that I'm distracted... during
that time and that after that time we left believe Michael because
he let it go so long, that makes sense if the issue
is that they were debating whether I paid him at all. Here
תוספות Tosafot points out it's a very different issue. We're debating what
did we agree upon a week ago. So number one I'm less
it's not like I'm so distracted like I remember what we agreed
upon a week ago. Number two why does it matter that Michael
waited? Michael already clearly we agreed that I owe him at least
ten dollars and he was willing to wait for the ten dollars
so why does that prove that I don't owe him twenty? Right?
So the relevance of זמנו zmano and עבר זמנו is much less
relevant here when the debate is how much did we agree upon
rather than have I paid you or not. Okay? So that's at
least I mean I don't have a good answer to that. תוספות
Tosafot. raises that question but anyway that's why normally זמנו is relevant
and how we're applying it here. Yes?
I don't understand the מיגו where he says if he could say
it was his he's believed to say the price.
That's we just finished That's why it's going to be a proof
against we're not done with it. We're going to go back. That's
why it's going to be a proof against אביי. So that's exactly
what we're bringing.
Listen to the הלכה. halacha. A craftsman finished work. Yes.
Am I entitled to hold it until you pay me? Yeah. So
really what I should do then if I'm really saying twenty I
shouldn't just give it back.
Of course. Of course. Okay. So that's if you gave it back
then that's a תקנה takana of נשבע ונוטל. But if you didn't
you're believed the אומן uman is really believed to say how much
because מיגו he could say it's his. Now we're going to just
figure out what's the scenario and this is going to be the
question when does an אומן uman have a חזקה chazaka and when
doesn't he? היכי דמי Heichi dami what's the case? אי דאיכא עדים
I de'ika edim now maybe the case is that we didn't see
it in the hands of the אומן. uman Okay? And but there
are witnesses. Meaning it's a case where meaning that would be a
case that would work for אביי. Even if there are witnesses that
I gave it to Michael and we didn't see it in his
hands he's believed to say that it's his right? Because remember for
אביי all that matters is whether we saw it or not. And
this case here where we're debating how much I owe Michael is
a question where he would be believed to say it's his. So
one possibility is that there are witnesses but we didn't see it
in Michael's hand. That's an אביי possibility a רבא Rava possibility. אי
דאיכא עדים? I de'ika edim? Then the גמרא Gemara says but then
wait it can't be a case that there were witnesses I gave
it to Michael. ולחזי עדי מאי קאמרי Velachzei edei mai kaamri then
the עדים edim should have should know how much we stipulated. Let's
just ask the עדים edim what we stipulated. Okay so you could
make a case where the עדים edim saw me give it and
they didn't hear us say the price. But the גמרא Gemara anyway
thinks that that's not reasonable.
It's a funny thing about the עדים edim, saw what they said.
Isn't it a funny well that's true.
Okay. אלא לאו דליכא עדים Ela lav deleika edim it must be
so since it's it can't be since we're debating what we agreed
upon it must be there weren't witnesses. דקתני Dekatani אומן uman נאמן
ne'eman and we see that the אומן uman. is believed. So if
there's not witnesses it's only an interesting case to say that Michael
is believed if we're assuming not witnesses if we see it in
his hands. If there's not witnesses and we don't see it in
his hands right that's the obvious case that he's believed. So the
גמרא Gemara assumes that we're going to be making it an interesting
case that Michael's believed to say it's his. The interesting case is
either witnesses and not seeing it but we excluded that because if
there were witnesses there wouldn't be a debate how much I owed
them. So it's got to be
the other interesting case would be no witnesses and we did see
it. So and even so Michael is believed. אלא לאו דליכא עדים
Ela lav deleika edim it must be there's no witnesses. דקתני Dekatani
אומן uman. נאמן ne'eman and nevertheless Michael is believed. So why must
that be? מיגו דאי בעי אמר ליה לקוחה היא בידי נאמן נמי
אהגרא Migode'iba'i amar lei lekucha hi beyadi ne'eman nami ahigra it must
be since he could say he owned he purchased it he could
say that he's believed on how much the fee was. So since
it's not a case of witnesses it must be a case of
no witnesses and it must be an interesting case. It must be
a case of no witnesses that we saw it in Michael's hand
and Michael is still believed. So you see the עיקר ikar of
when he has a חזקה chazaka or not have a חזקה chazakah.
is based on whether there are witnesses. Because even though we saw
it in Michael's hand since there are no witnesses he's believed. So
the גמרא Gemara says doesn't that prove רבא's position that the עיקר
ikar is witnesses? So the גמרא Gemara says no no לעולם דליכא
עדים Le'olam deleika edim there's no witnesses והוא דלא ראה. vehu delo
ra'ah. It's not an interesting case. It's a boring case. The case
where Michael's believed to say how much we agreed upon was when
there are was just when there are
no witnesses and לא ראה. lo ra'ah. Okay right? So this is
a case. Meaning the only story about that that we're debating how
much we agreed upon in terms of him dry-cleaning says that he
could believe he's believed to claim that לקוחה היא בידי. lekucha hi
beyadi. It doesn't say what the scenario is. So that doesn't prove
anybody's position because it could be the most boring scenario possible that
both we don't see it in his possession and there are no
witnesses.
What does לקוחה היא בידי lekucha hi beyadi here mean? It means
that I could he could have said I bought it from you?
Yeah.
That is so not believable.
Well if there's no witnesses
and a dry-cleaner oh you didn't bring it for me to clean
I
You're only saying that because you're assuming that there's either evidence that
you gave it to him or that we're seeing it right now
in his possession.
You're relying on an assumption.
You go to a dry-cleaner and you say where's my coat? And
you say give me evidence I gave you my your coat? And
you say no. Says you see your coat in my possession? And
you say no. Says okay I'll tell you what. I'll admit that
I have your coat but I'm telling you that I bought it
from you. That's ridiculous. Why? I'll tell you why. No evidence that
you gave it to me and no evidence that it's currently in
my hand.
You're 100% except for one thing. It's a dry
cleaner, everybody gives...
A dry cleaner isn't allowed? A dry cleaner isn't allowed to buy?
All right, moving on. Okay, moving on. All right. Anyway, the point
is that
all that case proves is that there's times when he's believed, that
he does have a
חזקה. chazakah. But it doesn't prove it's an interesting
case, no witnesses and no evidence that he's holding on to it,
so it doesn't prove
רבא's position or the anti-רבא position. Okay, so let's go on. מתיב
רב נחמן בר יצחק. Mativ Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. Now רב נחמן
בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak is, that was the one attempt
to defend רבא. From here on in we're going to be rejecting
רבא. And it's all going to be about ראה. ra'ah. מתיב רב
נחמן בר יצחק: Mativ Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak: אומן אין לו חזקה.
uman ein lo chazakah. Our משנה, Mishnah, an אומן uman doesn't have
a חזקה. chazakah. אומן הוא דאין לו חזקה, uman hu de-ein lo
chazakah, האחר יש לו
חזקה.
ha-acher yesh
lo chazakah. Normal person in a similar circumstance would have a חזקה.
chazakah היכי דמי? heichi dami? אי דאיכא עדים, אחר אמאי יש לו
חזקה? i de-ika edim acher amai yesh lo chazakah?
According to רבא's position, right? That רבא's position is no חזקה chazakah,
with עדים, edim because either because it's both עדים edim and ראה,
ra'ah, so,
or even without ראה ra'ah possibility of המפקיד אצל חברו בעדים צריך
להחזירו בעדים. hamakfid etzel chaveiro be-edim tzarich lehachziro be-edim. But then it
has nothing to do with being an אומן. uman Any person that
you saw me give something to that person as a פקדון pikadon
and the person is still holding on to it can't say it's
his. And if you hold that if I give it to him
as a פקדון pikadon he's not believed to say he returned it,
then he's not believed even if I don't see it in his
hands. This issue that with עדים edim, that I gave it to
him as a פקדון, pikadon, right, he's not believed, has nothing to
do with his role as an אומן. uman. So therefore according to
רבא, it's not about אומן אין לו חזקה, uman ein lo chazakah,
it's המפקיד אצל חברו בעדים אין לו חזקה. hamakfid etzel chaveiro be-edim
ein lo chazakah. Okay? People understand it has nothing to do with
the guy's profession. So גמרא Gemara says: אי דאיכא עדים i de-ika
edim, אחר אמאי יש לו חזקה? acher amai yesh lo chazakah? אלא
לאו, ella lav, so it must be that it's not this. This
is all about we can prove you got it as פקדון, pikadon,
so you're not believed to say that you bought it, whether we
see it in your hand or don't see it in your hand.
It has nothing to do with the fact that that's your profession.
It must be this approach, that it's about ראה. ra'ah. And then
we could say a normal person who I see, and you know,
ראה ra'ah and no עדים, edim. right? So we have, I see
something that I knew was my coat in your hands. We have
no idea how it got to be in your hands. So that's
the key, it's no עדים. edim It's in your hands, we have
no idea how it got there. A normal person will assume חזקה
מה שתחת יד אדם הרי הוא שלו. chazakah mah she-tachat yad adam
harei hu shelo. It got there because you bought it. And an
אומן uman we're going to assume it got there because I gave
it to you to do work on it. Okay. So אלא לאו,
ella lav, let me just finish reading it, אלא לאו דליכא עדים,
ella lav dileka edim, דתני אומן אין לו חזקה. de-tani uman ein
lo chazakah.
So it must be that there's no witnesses and that the issue
of you being unique about the idea of being an אומן uman
is because you're an אומן. uman, A normal person would be believed,
you see me wearing your suit, there's no witnesses how I got
it, a normal person is believed to say I bought it. And
because I'm an אומן uman. I'm not believed to say I bought
it. There's a presumption that I got it because of, because I
got it to work on it, again assuming that it's the type
of thing that this אומן uman, would work on. Okay. So תיובתא
דרבא תיובתא. tyuvta de-Rava tyuvta. That contradicts רבא. The key is about
ראה. ra'ah. Yes.
If we understand רבא's retraction as retraction to the just as well,
then why isn't the answer to this question that when you have,
that when you are an אומן, uman that's the only case you
don't get a חזקה, chazakah. but if a
normal
person, I'm
sorry, yes, right.
I mean, especially if רבא's limited to this, right? Then any person,
there's עדים eidim, you got it as a פקדון pikadon and it's
still in your hands, of course you don't have a חזקה. chazakah.
That has nothing to do with being an אומן. uman, Right. Okay.
So right, so
this is the interesting case. I'm walking down the street with your
suit in my hand or wearing your suit, we have no idea
how I got it. If I'm a normal person, I'm believed to
say I bought it from you. If I'm an אומן, uman. I
am not.
Right, you said if it's a dry cleaner with your coat or
if it's a carpenter with your hammer. Exactly.
Right, right, right. Exactly. If it's a dry cleaner with your shoes,
he would be believed to say he bought it. Okay. Now moving
on. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. Now we got a very interesting ברייתא,
a
תוספתא tosefta from בבא קמא Bava Kamma which is just relevant because
it talks about an אומן uman. and this is a scenario that
actually happens from time to time. נתחלפו לו כלים בכלים בבית
האומן הרי זה ישתמש בהן. nitchelfu lo keilim be-keilim be-veit ha-uman harei
zeh yishtamesh bahen. You go to pick up your dry cleaning and
you get your winter coat and the guy gives it back to
you, and when you bring it home and you take the wrapping
off it, you see it's somebody else's winter coat. Okay. So but
it's the winter and you're freezing cold, so can you wear it?
הרי זה ישתמש בהן עד שיבוא הלז ויטול את שלו. harei zeh
yishtamesh bahen ad she-yavo halaz ve-yitol et shelo. Until the guy who
accidentally took yours brings it back, you can wear his.
Wait one minute. Read the next line. וזו אף היא אבדת המשתה.
Vezo af hi avedat hamishteh.
Let's say it got mixed up because everybody was going, it's interesting
how it brings you into the real life, right? They were going
to pay a שבעה shiva call and you had a whole big
pile of coats and you took the wrong one, or it's a,
you know, a wedding or whatever, right? And those types of cases,
הרי זה לא ישתמש בהן עד שיביא הלה ויטול את שלו. Harei
zeh lo yishtamesh bahen ad sheyavi halah veyitol et shelo. Then you
can't use the guy's coat you took accidentally and you have to
wait till he brings yours back and then you get yours back.
But I have to tell you, and David and I grew up
in the same שול, shul, it was like every other שבת Shabbos
they made an announcement, remember this? at the end of דאווענינג. davening.
Did anybody accidentally take home a 40 regular London Fog raincoat from
the coatroom? Anyway, so the question is, you took home the wrong
coat from שול, shul, it looked just like the other guys, are
you allowed to wear it or not? And the answer is you're
not. Okay, it's true that it's unfortunate that he has your coat,
but he hasn't given you permission to wear his, you know? And
if he hasn't given you permission to wear yours. All right, but
there's nothing you can do about that. Okay, so you gotta go
home in a sweater.
Last one there!
What can I tell you? You're not allowed to use somebody else's
things. Two rights don't make a wrong. Okay, two wrongs don't make
a right, excuse me. I got that reversed. Two rights also don't
make a right, but two wrongs don't make a right.
Okay, okay, so, okay, now the גמרא Gemara wants to know if
that's true because what's the logic, right? It feels a little unfair,
but we understand you can't use somebody's thing without permission. So how
is it different in the case of בית האומן? beit ha'uman? So
the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא? Mai shna
reisha umai shna seifa? What makes the first case different? What allows
you to use somebody else's garment in the case of the בית
האומן? beit ha'uman?
So אמר רב, Amar Rav, רב Rav says הוה יתיבנא קמיה דחביבי,
Hava yativna kamei dechavivi, I was sitting in front of my of
רב חייא, Rav Chiyya, my uncle, my beloved one, ואמר לי, Veamar
li, and he explained it to me in the following
way, רב חייא. Rav Chiyya. And וכי אין אדם עשוי לומר לאומן
מכור לי טליתי? Vechi ein adam asui lomar le'uman mechor li taliti?
So does a person never say to an אומן, uman, you know
what, keep my garment, sell it to somebody for me, give me
the proceeds? Okay, so that can happen from time to time. So
therefore what? So therefore what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, here's
what it imagines happens.
I'm the אומן. uman, Michael gave me his coat and he said
sell it for me. Okay. Then David comes in and David is
asking for his coat. All right, now I, what I did is,
I accidentally, I'm very, I really shouldn't be in this business because
I can't keep things straight. So when Eli came in and he
said and he asked for his coat back, I accidentally gave him,
well, I don't know if we have to even say that, but
let's say I accidentally gave him David's. David comes in and asks
for his coat, forget Eli, that's confusing. Okay. Michael says sell my
coat for me. David comes in and asks for his coat and
I give him Michael's coat. Okay.
So even though he doesn't
tell you, I give it to him because I think it's his.
Okay. So in that type of a case, David is entitled to
use the coat because it actually is Michael's to sell. I didn't
knowingly give it to David, I thought I was giving David back
his own coat. Okay. But in that case, you know, and I
really need, and I really should've sold this, and I, you know,
the רשב"ם Rashbam says it, I sold so, I sold maybe David's
coat to Eli, I got it all confused. Okay. So now Eli
has David's coat, David has Michael's coat, okay, but the bottom line
is that I had a right to give you that coat because
that coat was mine to sell. So therefore you can use it
until what?
Or he relinquishes possession to it and he told you to sell
it.
Yeah, but Michael's asking me to sell it for him and giving
it to me on consignment basically gave me that type of permission,
whether it made me fully an owner, whether it gave me that
degree of permission, but I'm now enough in control of that suit
that I can actually, so therefore if you accidentally get the wrong
coat or the wrong suit, we can hypothesize, now of course the
likelihood that it happened to work out that way, okay, but again
this is maybe with a little רחמנות rachmanus that you're having to
go without your coat until you can get it back. Okay. So
therefore we're prepared to speculate and hypothesize and say you know what,
maybe that coat you got was one that Michael had the right
to give to you.
And that's why you're not responsible, even if you get it from
the אומן.
If you get it from the אומן, you're allowed to keep wearing
it because we're going to assume that maybe that was the coat,
נעבעך nebech you're without a coat, and maybe there was actually one
that he had a right to lend out to you.
But as soon as we find out that it really wasn't
that coat, you'd have to give it back. Right.
And does, so do I have a responsibility to say this is
not really my coat?
Of course. Oh yeah, sure. Yeah, well right, meaning what you should
do is if you realize right away to Michael, you say that's
not my coat. I'm the dry cleaner.
I'm the dry cleaner,
I got confused.
I'm the dry cleaner. So if you realize right away and you
say to me hey that's not my coat, so if I say
ah don't worry you can use it, it's a loaner because I
have the right to give it
to
you. But but that's the point, you know, the same way that
somebody would say here take it, it's a loaner until you get
the other one back, so we're going to assume that the dry
cleaner is giving it to you has the right to give it
to you as a loaner. But that's not true if you're getting
your coat mixed up in a pile of coats in somebody's, you
know, in somebody's שבעה shiva house, right?
What I'm asking is what's my responsibility?
Your responsibility... oh, if you go home, I see...
you mean I take it as a loaner and I say, wait
wait wait, does this... do I have to say it's...
No, I see. I mean, yeah, I think that if you're standing,
it's a good point. I think if you're standing there right there
with me, I mean I don't, you know, it's an interesting question
על פי דין al pi din what your responsibility is, but it
would seem to me that you would have to like clarify it
if you're standing right there, right? But if you go home with
it and then you realize it, right? Then I think you don't
have to come back to me and clarify or whatever. I'm not
sure. It's a real... that's a very good question, like what's your
degree of responsibility to clarify the whole issue after you're gone home.
Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay. Okay. אמר רב פפיא בריה דרב נחמן: Amar Rav Papia
brei d'Rav Nachman: לא שנו אלא הוא, Lo shanu ela hu, אבל
אשתו ובניו לא. aval ishto u'vanav lo. Now where is that true?
That's only if the dry cleaner gave it to you himself. But
if the wife or the kids gave it to you, no. Why
not? So...
Meaning the wife and the kids...
His wife and kids were running the... were working in the shop
that day and they gave it to you. So the רשב"ם Rashbam
says it's because we say we assume they made a mistake and
they didn't give you the loaner, they just סתם stam mixed it
up. But why is that? We assume the wife and the kids
make more mistakes than the owner? So I would say it a
little bit differently. I would say that it's only the owner that
has that discretion, right? The owner was given the coat to sell,
he has the discretion how to use that coat and whether to
give it out as a loaner. The wife and kids who are
like his employees don't have that discretion. That's in general an interesting
case, you know, something happens to you, there's some mix-up at the
counter or at the restaurant, you know, and the person says, you
know, right, what happens if right, the actual person at the cash
register or the waiter says, don't worry about it, it's on the
house. You're not allowed to tell me it's on the house. It's
you know, it's not yours, you don't have that right, you don't
have that discretion. So here, right, that would... that seems to be
the issue. You'd have to say that they don't have the discretion?
Yeah, I mean unless... unless it's a case where we can assume
they have that discretion. Some places aren't they have discretion, right, under
some circumstances. Alright. So the גמרא Gemorah. says like this, אבל אשתו
ובניו לא. aval ishto u'vanav lo. הוא נמי לא אמרינן אלא דאמר
ליה טלית סתם. Hu nami lo amrinan ela d'amar leh tallit stam.
And here David clarifies a little bit your case. אבל טליתך לא.
aval tallit-cha lo. If I, if David comes for the coat and
I say, oh, here's your טלית tallit, back, and David looks and
he realizes it's not my טלית, tallit, then you have to give
it back to me. But if I say oh, here's the טלית,
tallit here, you know, then you can interpret that as I know
this isn't yours, this is a loaner. Okay. But if I say
your טלית tallit, and it's not your טלית, tallit then you know
I've made a mistake and you have to give it back to
me. The גמרא Gemara assumes that all the local shop owners are
very punctilious with the exact grammar they use to
describe...
I think the point more is that we're gonna try to give
David some latitude here, so we'll read it into the case if
it's
possible.
You think in the coat owner's case, in other words, he's saying
here's the cloak. Right? I mean I look at it and I
know it's not mine, right? So what, I just go along with
it? Because that way I can use it?
That's your question before. How much if you're standing right there do
you have to clarify? Yeah, I don't know. Are we saying now
you're home and do you have to take it? Yeah, it sounds
like since it's about טליתך tallit-cha and טלית tallit that you are
standing right there and you're making a decision on the spot. Do
I have to say something or not? Yeah, you're right, it does
sound a little bit like even on the spot, he just says
here's a cloak and you know it's not yours, you can somehow
assume it means a loaner. I don't know. I mean if it
was me, I would assume that my coat is still in the
back, not that somebody else has it, and I'd say, what do
you mean, this isn't mine, go find mine, right? Yeah. And then
if he goes to the back and he says, look, just take
it, here's a coat. Then I can take it. Okay.
So you can take it?
Yeah, meaning he says, I couldn't find yours, just take this, here's
a coat. Okay, I'm serious. Then you can do it.
I mean wouldn't they... wouldn't they really say please get my coat?
I'll try to get it back, but just take this. And you
can do it. Then you assume it's a loaner, yeah. David?
Yeah, I mean it seems to me that the case is clear
that the guy's left already...
Well, but the point that you have to distinguish between טליתך tallit-cha
and טלית sounds a little bit like you're just signing at the...
I don't know. I don't know. Anyway, it's a good question David
asks, which is what's your level of responsibility if you're standing right
there. Okay, אלא דאמר ליה טלית סתם, ela d'amar leh tallit stam,
אבל טליתך לא. aval tallit-cha lo. האי לאו טליתך היא. Hai lav
tallit-cha hi. Because this isn't yours, fine. אמר ליה אביי לרבא, Amar
leh Abaye le'Rava, תא אחוי לך רמאי דפומבדיתא, ta achvei lach rama'ei
d'Pumbedita, let me come and show
you these... these deceitful...
scoundrels of Pumbedita, how they try to, you know, how they cheat
people. Okay. מאי עבדי? Mai avdi? What do they do?
אמר ליה הבו סרבלאי. Amar leh hav sarbalai. If you say to
them... and here he actually did a little bit of a demonstration.
He says come, I'm going to show you, I'm going to try
to get my coat back from the dry cleaner. Okay, so he
went to the dry cleaner in Pumbedita and he says... Give me
my coat. So he says, well, לאו איתם מעולם, lav itam me'olam,
I don't know what you're talking about, you never gave me a
coat. Okay. And we decided before that you need to see it
in his hands before you can, otherwise he's
believed, right? So, הא איכא סהדי דחזיא גבך. ha ika sahadei d'chazya
gabach. I have
witnesses that have seen my coat in your possession, right? It was
a, you know, it was a black Armani 40 regular, okay? And
I have witnesses that saw you have that suit. So, and once
you saw, that's a case of ראה. ra'ah. Although he mentions עדים,
eidim do not confuse this with the עדים eidim here. The עדים
here was that I gave it to you at the dry clean.
The witnesses that saw it in your possession, they don't know how
it got in your possession, they, but that's a case of ראה.
ra'ah. Okay, so we're all going again with this position that the
עיקר ikar is ראה. ra'ah. So he says, I don't have it,
I don't know what you're talking about. He says, I have witnesses
that saw it in your
hands.
אמר ליה amar lei what?
ואמרי לה אביי, v'amrei lah Abaye, there you go. אמר ליה, amar
lei, איברא, ibra, it's, you know, I'm sorry, I skipped a line.
אמר ליה, amar lei, הא אחרינא הואי. ha achreina havai. No, that's
a different Armani 40 regular. What, you think there's only one? It's
only yours? That one's mine. That's not yours. Okay. So he says,
אפקינה ונחזינה. afkinah v'nechzinah. All right, produce it, let's take a look.
So witnesses, you know, if you produce it, we'll be able to
tell if it's mine or yours.
אמר ליה, amar lei, איברא לא מפקינא לה. ibra la mafkinah lah.
No, I'm sorry, I'm not going to do it. You can't go
ahead and demand that I go ahead and show you my, you
know, I have a right to privacy. You can't make these crazy
demands that I go ahead and show you my clothes. Or the
way the רשב"ם... Rashbam...
What is איברא? ibra?
In truth, like. Now the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says it is,
he's actually like taking a principled position. If you look at the
רשב"ם, Rashbam, he says,
איברא לא מפקינא מיניה, ibra la mafkinah mineih, two lines on the
bottom.
באמת לא אוציאנו בשביל טענותיך של הבל. be'emet lo otzienu bishvil ta'anotecha
shel hevel. אראה לך ממון אחרים. areh lecha mamon acheirim. So maybe
I'm not even claiming that suit as mine. I'm saying it's somebody
else's suit. I'm a dry cleaner, that's not yours, it's somebody else's
suit. It just looks like yours. I don't have your suit.
Okay. So you want me to show it to you? I have
to protect the privacy of my customers, right? It's like, you know,
when the federal gov, when the government wants to get, you know,
Microsoft or whatever. I'm sorry, we have to protect the privacy of
our customers. I'm not picking up. What?
You agree that he was wearing that suit?
No, they saw it גבך. gabach. They saw you, they saw it
by you. They saw it like in your possession. Okay. So look
at this, we can't prove it. They saw, but they saw somewhat
far. They can't, the witnesses can't testify it was my suit they
saw. And this guy, this scoundrel, is pretending that he's concerned about
the privacy of his customers and he's refusing to produce it. So
אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא says, שפיר קאמר ליה. shapir ka'amar
lei. What do you mean? That's a legitimate position. Just because somebody
comes, if you can't prove that it's your suit in his hands,
he has no obligation to go ahead and produce it. ראה תניא.
ra'ah tanyah. It's all about seeing it. And if you didn't see
the thing itself, then you don't have any proof. Okay? You're saying
they're a scoundrel. Maybe somebody is making this claim up, you know?
They have a right to not produce, you know, those things. אמר
רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, ואי חכים משוי ליה ראה. v'ee chakim
mashvei lei ra'ah. Now רב אשי Rav Ashi says, okay, so again,
it's true. Maybe, you know, that's how things work. People do have
rights and the rights are to protect unscrupulous people. But then unscrupulous
people will use those rights and those protections, you know, to be
unscrupulous. So how do you know what any particular case is? So
רבא is saying we can't know, but they're within their legal rights
to say that.
But if they did have ראה, ra'ah,
it was not a sufficient ראה. ra'ah. You saw
something... Again, what's the... They saw a coat that looked just like
yours, but they could not identify it as yours. And therefore the
dry cleaner was believed to say, yes, it was the same brand,
it was the same thing, but it wasn't yours.
But what they saw wasn't yours.
It was George's coat.
It was an insufficient ראה.
ra'ah. It was enough of a ראה ra'ah to give us suspicion,
but it was insufficient for the evidence. And רבא is saying, okay,
suspicion is suspicion, this guy is still within his rights to not
produce it. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב אשי, amar Rav
Ashi, ואי חכים משוי ליה ראה. v'ee chakim mashvei lei ra'ah. Now,
if you're smart, you can try to turn this into a ראה
ra'ah case. Meaning, you're here, the guy who's being, you know, who's,
the dry cleaner is stealing your coat and claiming he never got
it, it's somebody else's. You can
try to use a way to get him to produce it. Okay,
what would be the way to get him to produce it? To
show it to you. Okay, the following way. דאמר ליה אמאי תפסת
ליה לאו משום דאית לי גבך. d'amar lei amai tafasta lei lav
mishum d'it li gabach. You say to the dry cleaner, look, you
say, between me and you, right? We know this is my coat.
But why are you holding on to it? It must be because
you must know that I owe you some back, you know, right?
I owe you bills, you know, I've owed you money that I
haven't paid up. So I'll tell you what. We'll settle the debt,
okay? I'll pay you up and then give it to me. Okay.
But of course, then he'll say, then he'll say, give me the
money first.
Okay. So this is what I'm going to say. I'll say, so,
so it must be because I owe you money. That's why you're
holding, that's why... This coat, this is a fur coat, this is
whatever, mink, this is worth ten thousand dollars. I owe you, you
know, I owe you maybe a thousand. It's not fair. Let's bring
it out, let's get some people to assess its value, and then
you know I'll pay you for the difference or whatever it is,
but it's not fair that you're holding on to the whole thing.
Okay? Or you'll pay me for the difference, however we want to
work it. Okay? ושיימינו שקול את דידך ושקול אנא דידי. V'shaiminu shkol
at didach v'shkol ana didi. You'll take what's yours and I'll take
what's mine because you don't want to really be a thief. I
understand why you're holding on to it, so let's be fair about
it. So then Michael will bring it out, okay? And we'll get
witnesses to assess its value and at that moment the witnesses have
seen that it's my coat in his hands and then I'll be
able to take it because he doesn't have a חזקה. chazakah. So
of course the point is don't try to what's it, it's like
don't try to cheat a cheater or some other phrase like that.
Don't try to some anyway he'll be too smart for you. Okay.
So אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב אויה לרב אשי מצי אמר
ליה, Amar lei Rav Acha brei d'Rav Avya l'Rav Ashi matzi amar
lei, what he'll
say back to you is לא צריכנא לשומא דידך. Lo tzrichna l'shuma
didach. Who needs you to assess it? כבר שמוה קמאי דקמך. Kvar
shamuha kamai d'kamach. I've had other people assess it and I know
it's worth your debt and I'm still holding on to it and
I'm still claiming that it's mine. Okay? So he's not going to
agree to it.
If he's smart, he's smart enough to do this device, you know,
smart enough to do this or that. Right. Don't try to outfox
the fox, some statement like that, there's some line that I can't
remember. Yeah. So even some big place with a great ישיבה yeshiva
has cheaters? Well, sometimes the places that can support big ישיבות yeshivas
are big metropolitan cities and therefore, you know, that's where a lot
of this type of stuff goes on.
It's גנבי דתלמידי חכמים, ganvei d'talmidei chachamim, it's גנבי דמכבסתא, ganvei d'machbesta,
dry cleaner.
Okay. Anyway, that was a very nice little illustration, but what it
did was it reinforced the idea that אומן אין לו חזקה במקום
ראיה, uman ein lo chazakah bimkom re'iyah, but that ראיה really has
to mean that you saw it and can identify it. As long
as you can't identify it as yours, the guy can always claim
it's somebody else's. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אריס אין לו חזקה. Aris ein lo chazakah. We're done with the
אומן, then from בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash.
Yeah. Okay, yeah, I know that was a very relevant case. Now
we're on to the אריס. aris. A sharecropper does not have a
חזקה. chazakah? אריס
אין לו חזקה. Aris ein lo chazakah. אמאי? Amai? Why not? עד
האידנא פלגא והשתא כולא. Ad idna palga v'hashta kula. What do you
mean he doesn't have a חזקה? chazakah. I understand that he anyway
was working in the field and we know he was an אריס,
aris, but until now he's been keeping half to himself and giving
the half to the בעל הבית. ba'al habayis's So now for three
years he's been keeping it all to himself. That should be pretty
prima facie evidence that he's no longer an אריס, aris, that he's
a legitimate owner.
Like how do they know exactly? They see...
Yeah. Somehow it used to be that the בעל הבית's ba'al habayis
trucks would roll up and he'd put load it on and now
we see him bringing it into his... If you have that type
of evidence that he's now harvesting it all for himself, okay, so
that should be pretty good evidence that he's no longer an אריס.
aris. So the
גמרא Gemara says השתא כולא, hashta kula, אמר רבי יוחנן באריסי בתי
אבות. amar Rabbi Yochanan b'arisei batei avos. What we're dealing with is
with it's like a
traditional where people have sharecropping as a permanent institution. Okay, this family
has always been sharecroppers on this guy's land going back for generations.
Why is that relevant? Because if I hire my sharecroppers each year,
there's no way I would let
my, these workers that turn over every year, that I would let
them go a year taking it all for himself in exchange for
the next year giving it all to me, because it's it's
turnover every single year. But if this family for generations has been
sharecropping my land, then I'm willing to give a little latitude and
I'm willing to say, you know what? For the next three years
keep it all for yourself and then three years afterwards give it
all to me. And I'm willing to have that trust that that
will happen because, and you're willing to have that trust, or we
did the reverse. First three years give it all to me, next
three take it all for yourself. Right? You the sharecropper are willing
to give me that trust because we have this very long-standing relationship.
So in that type of a case it's possible that you're there
for three years and you're taking all of the produce and you're
still a sharecropper. Okay, because it's a more permanent institution. So but
a normal אריס aris would have a חזקה. chazakah. So that's pretty
interesting. It's a very significant limiting of the case of the משנה.
Mishnah. אמר רב נחמן אריס שהוריד אריסין תחתיו יש לו חזקה. Amar
Rav Nachman aris she-horid arisin tachtav yesh lo chazakah. Now let's say
we're talking about this right, exactly. Let's say we're talking about this
sharecropping family, okay, and that normally doesn't
have a חזקה. chazakah, This בתי אבות batei avos family normally doesn't
have a חזקה, chazaka. because there could be a presumption that we're
just given the right for three years and then we'll, no, but
we'll take three years and the בעל הבית ba'al habayit, take three
years. But during these three years, not just I work it, what
I do is I bring in a lot of
sub sharecroppers, okay? So they're going to work my
field, they're going, I'm just going to sit back and relax and
I'm going to get my percentage, they're going to do their... all
of the work. So if I normally get fifty percent, they're going
to get forty percent, I'll take ten percent because I have the
rights and I'm sort of letting them do it. Okay, so in
that type of a
case, אריסי דאריסי תחתיו, Arisei de'arisi tachtav, יש לו חזקה. yesh lo
chazaka. In that case you have a חזקה. chazaka? Why? מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? What's the reason?
דלא עביד איניש דנחית אריסי לארעיה ושתיק delo avid inish dinachtit arisei
le'arveih v'shatik because the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains this
in this type of a case where I am giving it to
other people, if I am, hold on let me just read the
רשב"ם Rashbam again to make sure I'm explaining this correctly. Hold on.
Yeah,
this
is interesting.
Right, because the owner of the field did not give permission for
these sub-contractors and you know, who knows that he's comfortable with these
strangers working his land. Alright, so he would not have been silent
had it not been that the אריס Aris had really bought the
land.
Three years is a חזקה? chazaka.
מיד mi'yad or three years? No, three years. Okay.
Maybe people don't like it, why wouldn't he protest right away?
That's true, but in any case it's a חזקה. chazaka. Okay. But
the basic point is, and that phrase that I think Chanan gave
us a while ago, adverse possession was a good one, from the
perspective of the אריס בתי אבות, Aris batei avot, this is totally
with his permission. But from the perspective of the בעל הבית, ba'al
habayit it's not with his permission, it's adverse possession. These people are
on his land that he never gave the אריס Aris permission to
sub-contract, okay, and he would not have been quiet unless the אריס
Aris had really bought it. Okay, so
דלא עביד איניש דנחית אריסי לארעיה ושתיק. delo avid inish dinachtit arisei
le'arveih v'shatik. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, okay, that's true about
that
case, but אריס שחלק לאריסי aris shechilek la'arisei אין לו חזקה. ein
lo chazaka. But if it's not that he sort of sub-contracted and
stayed at home and just took his ten percent off the top,
but he actually
divided it with אריסין. arisin. Now, what's the difference between חלק chilek
and הורי תחתיו? hori tachtav? Well, הורי תחתיו hori tachtav means in
my stead, I'm not doing anything. חלק chilek means I get together
other people and I am going to be working with them and
I'm giving them different jobs to do, but I'm an active participant
in the whole process. Okay, I'm the foreman, I'm working with them,
we're working together, but they're working with me. In that type of
a
case, okay, then
the בעל הבית ba'al habayit would be okay with it because the
בעל הבית ba'al habayit trusts me, and if I'm present and working
with them, he knows it's under my direct supervision and he trusts
me, therefore אין לו חזקה. ein lo chazaka. Because therefore it's not
adverse possession and we could assume that I'm just doing it as
an אריס Aris and not as an owner. Okay? אריס שחלק לאריסין
Aris shechilek la'arisin אין לו חזקה. chazakah מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? אימר
הרמנא בעלמא שוויה, eimar harmana b'alma shavya, הרמנא בעלמא שוויה. harmana b'alma
shavya. He just he gave him permission. Okay, the בעל הבית gave
permission to the אריס Aris to bring other people in if the
אריס Aris can't do it himself as long as the אריס Aris
is actively involved. So since that's not adverse possession, there would not
be a חזקה.
chazakah, הרמנא Harmana is
what?
Is permission. Permission, yeah, license. הרמנא בעלמא שוויה?
Harmana
b'alma shavya?
שלח ליה? Shelach lei?
He gave him... No, שלח
ליה shelach lei
is no...
הרמנא בעלמא שוויה. Harmana b'alma shavya. He just he gave him that
permission, okay, he gave him that
authority. Okay. שלח ליה רב נחמן בר רב חסדא לרב נחמן בר
יעקב. Shelach lei Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda l'Rav Nachman bar Yaakov.
רב נחמן בר רב חסדא Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda sent to
רב נחמן בר יעקב. Rav Nachman bar Yaakov. Now, by the way,
there's a great little תוספות Tosafot here. I just want to show
you this. Look at this תוספות. Tosafot שלח ליה רב נחמן בר
יצחק... Shelach lei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak... there are two רב נחמן,
Rav Nachmans, right? רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak and
רב נחמן בר רב חסדא Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda and רב
נחמן בר יעקב. Rav Nachman bar Yaakov. So תוספות Tosafot says רב
נחמן סתם שבכל הגמרא, Rav Nachman stam shebechol haGemorah, when you say
סתם stam רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, which רב נחמן Rav Nachman are
we referring to? הוא רב נחמן בר יעקב. Hu Rav Nachman bar
Yaakov. It's רב נחמן בר יעקב. Rav Nachman bar Yaakov. How does
תוספות Tosafot know that?
תדע שבכל הגמרא לא תמצא רב נחמן בר יעקב נזכר שמו ושם
אביו, Teda shebechol haGemorah lo timtza Rav Nachman bar Yaakov nizkar shemo
v'shem aviv, you never have the full name, רב נחמן בר יעקב,
Rav Nachman bar Yaakov, אלא אם כן יש רב נחמן אחר אצלו,
ela im ken yesh Rav Nachman acher etzlo, unless there's another רב
נחמן Rav Nachman in the discussion. So only when there's another רב
נחמן Rav Nachman will you find the name רב נחמן בר יעקב,
Rav Nachman bar Yaakov, but otherwise it'll never be there. So it
must be because סתם stam רב נחמן Rav Nachman is רב נחמן
בר יעקב. Rav Nachman bar Yaakov. So we don't have to explicate
it unless there's another רב נחמן Rav Nachman that we're talking about.
So brilliant, isn't it? Okay. It's a puzzle pretty amazing that you
could know all of ש"ס Shas and know
that the only time it says רב נחמן בר יעקב Rav Nachman
bar Yaakov is when another
רב
נחמן Rav Nachman is around. Alright, anyway. Used a computer. Exactly, yeah.
תוספות Tosafot. had בר אילן. Bar Ilan. תוספות's Tosafot head was a
בר אילן. Bar Ilan. Okay. So anyway,
back to the גמרא. Gemara, That was just an interesting little
interlude. שלח ליה רב נחמן בר רב חסדא לרב נחמן בר יעקב.
Shelach lei Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda l'Rav Nachman bar Yaakov. ילמדנו
רבינו, Yelamdeinu Rabbeinu, let our master teach us, אריס מעיד aris me'id.
או אינו מעיד? o eino meid? Ah, we're always getting back to
that. If in these types of cases when you have a vested
interest or might have a vested interest, could you testify? So therefore
I am here, the אריס, aris I'm working Michael's land, and now
comes along Eli and says that land was always mine, it wasn't
Michael's, so can I testify that I have evidence that I know
it was Michael's land? Maybe I testify that I was working... Not
necessarily for three years, so that's a חזקה for Michael, whatever it
is, you know? So can I testify or not? So what would
you say? Can an אריס aris, testify who the owner of the
land is?
Well, you're supposed to be—here, נוגע בדבר, nogeah badavar, right?
I would totally think you're נוגע בדבר. nogeah badavar. Who the owner
is determines what the terms are, whether he's a nice guy, not
a nice guy, right, how flexible, how easy it is to work
with.
And if he can even be there.
Imagine you asked that question: could an employee testify to who his
boss
is? Right? It totally matters to you who your boss is. Alright,
anyway, so אריס מעיד. aris me'id. So that's bizarre. That's, I would
totally think it should be obvious you shouldn't be allowed to. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. הוי יתיב רב יוסף קמיה,
Havi yativ Rav Yosef kameih, Rav Yosef was sitting there, ואמר ליה,
ve'amar leih, הכי אמר שמואל, hachi amar Shmuel, אריס aris מעיד. meid
Yeah, an אריס aris can testify. So it sounds crazy. But it's
weird to say no. It's also weird, like,
because he has direct knowledge. So what? Remember the people of the
town whose ספר תורה sefer Torah was stolen and nobody could testify
to it? Yeah, so, alright. Other people could see the guy. I
don't think—anyway, imagine
you're seeing your employer and testifying in his behalf on something that
it's your land. But the land, by saying that it's this person's
land, you're basically allowing Michael to continue to be your employer. If
I say yes, this land always belonged to Michael, I'm allowing Michael
to continue to be my employer as opposed to, right? Let's take
a look. Okay. So the גמרא says, והתניא אינו מעיד, vehatanya eino
me'id, we got a ברייתא that says you can't.
לא קשיא. lo kashya. הא דאיכא פירא בארעא הא דליכא פירא בארעא.
ha de'ika peira be'ar'a ha delika peira be'ar'a. So the גמרא says,
no, no, no. Here's the point. The fruit is ready to be
harvested. I spent the whole, the whole, whatever it is, fall working
this land. The fruit is ready to be harvested. So if it's
Michael's land, I'll get and I'll get my fifty percent, I'll harvest
it and get my fifty percent. If it's Eli's land, then I
wouldn't have been working that land with an אריס aris relationship. I
would have been יורד לתוך שדה חברו שלא ברשות yored letoch sdei
chaveiro shelo birshut and I would have been paid lower wages. Okay?
So by proving that it's Michael's land, it allows me to get
my, you know, my full fifty percent, as opposed to, as opposed
to with Eli. Then I can't be מעיד. me'id. But if there's
no fruit on the land and it's not a question about gaining
from the past, you know, getting paid for the past, it's a
question about the future, so then I am believed.
Wait, it's winter
now, but I worked it? Whatever, it's all been harvested. Now we're
debating whose land it is and the נפקא מינה nafka mina is
who will I be working for next year? Okay? There's no נפקא
מינה nafka mina for this year.
Where does the fruit go then? Because if it was Eli's, then
you might—you
know, that's an interesting point that you
might—that's a very interesting point that I don't know. Maybe then it
would be like המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, I'm not sure. Michael raises
a good point, even if the fruits have been harvested, right, you
know, there might be consequences to it. But let's bracket that for
now. It's a good point. But let's assume that the issue is
just going forward, okay? So then I am believed. Now why am
I believed since it still matters to me whose land I'm working?
So the גמרא says—so if
you—so if you take a look, not the גמרא, the רשב"ם. Rashbam.
So if you take a look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, the
רשב"ם Rashbam says—yeah, let's look at תוספות. Tosafot תוספות also
says it. הא דאיכא פירא בארעא. ha de'ika peira be'ar'a. תוספות says,
לא יעיד דנוגע בעדותו הוא, lo ya'id denogeah be'eduto hu, לפי שהיה
נותן לו למחצה לשליש ולרביע, lefi shehayah noten lo lemachetza lishlish uleravia,
ואם יזכה בה האחר הרי שלא ברשות ירד ויהא ידו על התחתונה.
ve'im yizkeh bah ha'acher harei shelo birshut yarad veyehei yado al hatachtonah.
אבל לית פירא בארעא, aval leit peira be'ar'a, but if there's no
fruit, לא חיישינן שמא יסלקנו דכמה שדות ימצא לאריסות. lo chaishinan shema
yesalkennu dekamah sdot yimtza le'arisut. Alright, so what if Eli doesn't want
me to continue? Michael would continue having me as an אריס. aris.
Maybe Eli won't. Plenty of fish in the sea, plenty of fields
in the ישיבה, yeshiva, I'll work for somebody else. I gotta tell
you, I really find that so hard to
accept. Right? Like, not everybody gets the opportunity to be a sharecrop—a
perfect competition assumption. Right, exactly!
It's—that's a nice way of putting it. Right, exactly! Like, why can
we assume that? Why should we assume even if I could find
somebody who'll hire me? Forget that! Even if I know Eli is
promising to hire me, maybe Michael's a better boss than Eli. I
mean, if the גמרא said before there's an issue of
הראשון נוח לי והשני קשה הימנו, harishon noach li vehasheni kasheh heimennu,
what is it, הראשון נוח לי והשני קשה הימנו, harishon noach li
vehasheni kasheh heimennu, right? That based on, like, you know, the—so we're
aware of those different things. It's not just you can exchange them
and they're all the same.
A new sharecropper might make me give my soup back.
Anyway, so
I really do not understand why this is not considered נוגע בעדות.
nogeah be'edut. It could be because it's maybe all future-oriented, maybe some
of those cases before was it a question of who is my
current בעל חוב? ba'al chov? Here it's a question of what's going
to be in the future, so therefore that's not enough of a
concrete and a present נוגע בדבר, nogeah badavar, right? So there could
be something of that aspect, which the רשב"ם Rashbam discusses a little
bit. Alright, so let's try to get a little further.
I
love that.
But it seems to me like even if the sharecropper says this
is his land, right, the person he's
working for, it's not really proof. It's just he—no,
no, no.
He might have evidence. First of all, he could testify that he's
been working it for three years, the חזקה, you know?
I testify you saw, whatever, you saw sale or something like that.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
All right, so now we're going to get to other cases, which
is going to sound bizarre that this is not a נוגע בעדות,
nogaya b'eidus, and a lot of them might be based on the
same principle of that if it's not an immediate benefit, even if
there's a future possible benefit, it's not considered. Where is
the
ק kof for the סימנא, simana, עמק? Omek? What? Where's the ק
kof for the—? We're getting to it. ערב מעיד ללווה. Areiv me'id
l'loveh. Yeah, so that's the ע. ayin. A—what do you call it?
A cosigner, a guarantor can testify to a—to the
ללווה, loveh, והוא דאית ליה ארעא אחריתי. v'hu d'is lei ara achriti.
The ע ayin is ערב, areiv, the
מ mem is מלווה, malveh, the ל lamed is לוקח, lokeach, and
the ק kof is קבלן. kablan. Next page. So let's do it.
Boy, I'm losing
my voice. ערב מעיד ללווה והוא דאית ליה ארעא אחריתי. Areiv me'id
l'loveh v'hu d'is lei ara achriti. So let's bring some other players
into this. I guaranteed Gloria's loan, okay? And now, and she's now,
and she owes money to Charlie there, okay? And now David is
coming and David is saying one of Gloria's fields is my field,
it's not Gloria's. And I'm trying to testify on behalf of Gloria
and say no, no, no, that's Gloria's field. Now, why do I
stand to gain by getting involved in that debate whose field it
is? So that he can take the field and you don't have
to be on the hook? Because when Charlie comes to collect the
loan, if Gloria doesn't have money and Gloria doesn't have any fields
to give Charlie, Charlie is coming to me, okay? So I want
to create as much buffer between me and Charlie as possible. So
therefore, I want Gloria to have that field so that Charlie can
collect from that field and not come to me. Okay, so how
can I testify that that's
Gloria's? והוא דאית ליה ארעא אחריתי. v'hu d'is lei ara achriti. If
she has another field, then there still remains some buffer, and therefore
by saying the second field is hers, that's not really נוגע בעדות.
nogaya b'eidus. Now of course the רשב"ם Rashbam says, what do you
mean? It's a bigger buffer, right? It's two fields instead of one
field. So again, this is where the רשב"ם Rashbam says yes, of
course there are scenarios, but a lot of things have to happen.
Gloria has to have no cash on hand, she has to have
no—this field that she does have has to no longer be like
available or whatever, and then—so since there's like—well, that's not a lot,
that's true, but anyway. But yes, but—and for them to be able
to collect,
doesn't all ארעא משעבדת, ara meshubedis, and therefore not only does the
land not have to be in their possession, but even when it
goes into the next person's possession, it—or doesn't the creditor collect it
from first?
Right, but if the guarantor, I think as soon as the land
is not in Gloria's possession, the guarantor can come to me without
being—but he might have the option, I have to double check on
that about when he goes
to—there's an opinion that he can go to the ערב areiv right
away, there's that opinion too.
Well, we're going to get to that with the קבלן. kablan. Hold
on, let me double check that. Hold on.
Oh no, no, no, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, sorry, thank you David
for correcting that. No, the point is not just that Gloria will
sell the land, but that that land will be collected by another
creditor. Gloria's got a lot of creditors out there, okay? So my
concern here is because you're right, if Gloria sold it, then you're
right, thank you, then Charlie could go with the lien to that
other land. Okay, so Gloria has—so by creating—what—so I want to have
Gloria have as many lands as possible, it's a great buffer. But
as long as she's got one other land, for Charlie to still
get access to me, a lot of things have to happen. First
of all, she has to have no cash, and second of all,
another creditor has to come and collect that—seize that land that she
has, and then that exposes me to Charlie. So even though it's
possible, because it's in the future and it's not—and it's not definite,
that's not considered enough of a benefit. Okay, so that's not considered
something to prevent me from testifying that this other land is in
Gloria's possession. Yes.
That raises an interesting
question. When one collects from land with a
lien on it, right, one is not simply considered a purchaser of
that land, meaning—correct, meaning when creditors are competing, then you collect and
I collect from you, but there is an order of the creditors
that is based on that, that's the most—wait, let's see, latest loan
documented—well, whoever lent the money last, right, collects the remaining
land—I have to think it through, but yes, but you are correct,
the basic point is when I took something for loan, another creditor
can't take it from me because then we'll just go in a
circle. Okay, but there is—but thank you for pointing that out. Okay,
but yes, so thank you, yes. So Gloria, if Gloria sold it,
I would still be protected, but if another creditor took it, that
exposes me. All right, so let's read just one more which is
easy and then we'll do the other two
tomorrow. מלווה מעיד ללווה והוא דאית ליה ארעא אחריתי. Malveh me'id l'loveh
v'hu d'is lei ara achriti. So, it's a more straightforward case.
I lent Michael money. Michael has a couple plots of land. Comes
along Eli and he wants to claim one of those plots is
his, right? I would like Michael to have as much land as
possible because when it comes my time to collect the land, I
want to have as much land available to choose from. Okay, but
the point is is that at the end of the day, as
long as Michael has enough land left for me to collect, I
am not seen as benefiting from saying that this additional plot is
in Michael's possession. Why? Because for me to again not collect from
Michael would mean that when it's time to collect Michael has no
cash, no available assets other than the land, and that the one
land that he has left even after Eli takes this one, that
one land some other creditor has taken it. So because it requires
all of those circumstances, me keeping this plot of land in Michael's
hand is not considered enough to make me נוגע בעדות. nogei b'eidus.
Okay and we will pick up with the other two tomorrow. You
can testify?
Just for context, I know these things just to make sure. What?
Meaning you can testify anything, including that? Yeah. Meaning even though you
are already biased. No, in that sense.